I am presenting on the writers project
and kind of a subproject of that
which I'm calling drifts.
And so drifts is a
sorry.
So this is the writers project.
And I'm just going to actually
open up the gallery.
And so it is a gallery of conceptual code
sketches designed to explore
the medium of the text editor.
In this collection,
the text editor is variously a tool
for the production of new textual forms,
or a playful experience
of language mediation that responds to
and furthers critical arguments
based off of theories of writing.
It's a series of computer artworks
inspired by conceptual poetics
and process art.
Many can be thought of as a caricature
of algorithmically mediated writing,
and it's an in progress gallery, so I'm
constantly adding new of these editors.
I'll just open a couple up
to kind of showcase.
So this is an editor
that if you type with it.
It appears kind of like another text
editor or word processor.
But if you try and use a delete key,
it doesn't work.
You can't delete any words
and you just get these smudges instead.
Let's see.
There's this other one, which if you type,
you can type things. But
once you
once you delete, you don't fully delete
the text.
More like a pencil than a than
the pen are kind of
non-material, or what Derrida called
having removed the trace of materiality
from text editing.
Here's one that if you.
You write a word,
it will ask you
if you're sure that you meant that.
Again,
more of a joke.
And yeah, and there's a bunch here.
So we'll get into some more of them.
And let's see.
Presentation.
Here are some of the theory texts
that the project responds to.
I'm not going to do all so much on this.
And then this is drifts.
So this is kind of a attempt
to make this writing
sandbox into something closer to a game
in the traditional sense.
Players
author a series of these concrete poems
with a different
one of each of the 60 editors,
or 60 or more editors
that exist in the writers project.
Each page
then kind of asks the player task them
with editing
or recombining their previous page
with a kind of a different constraint
that you'll learn master as a tool, or
just kind of be confused by in some cases
on this one, it's
one that will move
through a cycle of synonyms.
Where you write this.
Hopefully this is large enough to see,
and once you do write a poem or whatever,
I it only you only get
one of the cycled versions of each word.
And then in the next text editor,
it will have
you kind of alter that
or edit it or play with it.
This is a text editor
that only once words
that don't occur in the dictionary
and otherwise will mark them up.
So you might
edit there once you keep going.
I'm just going to do one more here.
This is a game of what I'm calling text
dress formally poetries.
And essentially you take that run off the
the errors that you made according
to those last editors
and play kind of the scheme of textures,
except for instead of the constraints
of like block shapes, you're playing
with the constraints of of words
as you see them.
So you'll kind of place
all erasures recyclable.
So you kind of play this game of waitress
cycle materials together.
Okay then.
So each line as it gets
written gets taken into this poem,
and I'll just submit that and so on
and so forth.
Once you're finished,
you can actually print this
like chapbook and kind of see
how how this thing progresses.
Cool.
So yeah.
So the project is kind of practice
based research for my PhD.
It's also conceptual art
or any of these things.
It's a way to explore
kind of what we want from our text editing
environments.
What Lillian von Bertram
really called systems interrogation,
or a platform to think about
how our language is produced, where words
come from.
And like the readers project of Daniel
How and John Kelly,
for which this project is named,
to ask questions about textual artifacts
from within a networked environment
of interrelated mediators of expression.
This includes
how spellcheck and autocorrect
are involved
with the production of identity
thinking
through some critical literacy claims.
And I've just been reading
a lot of concrete poetry
which decompose here, called
the tension of thing words in space time
and its associated theory.
Kinetic poetry,
meanwhile, is often theorizes
continuing concrete poetry's attention
to the materiality of language
within a contemporary, that is to say,
digitally mediated landscape of writing.
And Katherine Hayles,
thinking through Kaylee
Glazier, William Carlos Williams
and others, has posited
that digital poems may be best
thought of as machines to organize time,
and Hayles is referred to the means
by which kinetic poems, poetry that moves,
turns us from a conception of word
as thing to an idea of word as process.
Kinetic poetry is only one form
of the electronic forms
that showcases algorithmic processes,
but algorithmic
processes
surround our writing environments.
Everest Pipkin has taught a course
last year
that suggested that the web browser
is already a game engine, and
along these lines,
I want suggest that sorry,
that the text editor
is already a kinetic poem, or rather,
to take a looser and more accurate
position that the text editor is already
a kinetic poetry engine, or at least
with a little tweaking can be made.
We can borrow the esthetic forms
of kinetic poetry
and the game
engine affordances of the modern browser
to emphasize different processes
by which we shape language.
So what we're seeing here
is one of my early experiments
in moving words, in response to the player
writer's keystrokes.
And here is
that same editor that we saw earlier.
It replaces words with synonyms as they
appear in various online dictionaries.
And this type of process oriented
thinking that kinetic language is
said to lead to
is shared by contemporary writing pedagogy
with roots and Fluxus and process art.
And thinking about this process
is exactly what literacy scholars like
Hermanson and SA, Bradley,
Robinson, and Lander and Burris emphasize
as a way to push back on the imaginaries
of AI writing technologies,
which I'll get into a in a minute.
Let's see, how am I doing on time?
Yeah.
And so essentially, this editor lets us
kind of read the dictionary critically,
the kinetic texts partly
serving to put on display the automaticity
of autocorrect.
And continuing this.
Yeah.
The project is thinking
through the representation
of language within text editors
as concrete kinetic form.
And Allison Parrish also did this in her
essay on the visual representation
of spell Check.
The common squiggly underlines to her
evincing
twisted rope signs of bondage.
Spell check
here is considered a ubiquitous form of
AI writing interference, and I think
Allison is presenting in the session,
which is.
And so this gets us into what
Bradley Robinson
and other literacy scholars
refer to as automated writing technology.
And what they think through with terms
such as Andreyevich
is notion
of the computational unconsciousness,
stating that autonomous writing technology
encodes global digital infrastructures
that bear the stamp of gender abled
and racial oppression
in the new autonomous model of literacy
borrowed from delusion.
Theories of writing.
Writers are conceptualized
as emergent in a relational field, rather
than as autonomous subjects at the center
of experience, learning, and knowledge.
Pedagogically,
it becomes important to consider
how students identity is transformed
by writing and lens by the processes
and systems that they write through.
This means opening the processes
and texts employed by writing systems
for analysis.
Getting at the critical notion
of resistance, Robinson writes
that only once it is understood
that automated writing technologies
are sensibly designed to assist us
may in fact also resist us,
so we can then better understand our
capacity for resisting them.
And let's see, how are we doing on time?
I don't want to.
Step.
Maybe have.
A look.
I think I think it might be a 15 minutes
already so I can cut off here.
This is a text editor
that's like highlighting.
Yeah.
Again,
the that resistance of the text editor.
And here highlighting words
that don't occur in Finnegans Wake.
Again, kind of a critical design joke.
Cool.
Oh, sorry.
Did I already way overstep my time?
Okay, thanks.
Got it. Yeah.
This is why you don't mix up
all of your slides a few minutes
before the before the talk, but, yeah, so
I could talk a little bit
more about drifts or a text dress.
One thing
that I really tried to pay attention
to in making these editors is process.
So a lot of these text editors are older
versions of previous text editors.
If I click this,
I can see the older versions.
And so you can see like the kind of way
that process has occurred in each
each of these text editors
have slightly different characteristics
and the way it mediates constraints
or thinks about language.
So I encourage people to play with this.
This is up as part of the gallery.
And yeah.
And the last thing that I want to mention
is that I'm hoping to open
this as like a journal,
kind of to accept submissions from others.
This is like the template
that I'm usually start from when I'm
designing these text editors.
And it's pretty simple, I think, to extend
using JavaScript and CSS.
So stay tuned for that to
hopefully start accepting submissions
at some point in the future.
And midst
is a great a great thing to point to to.
I almost mentioned it here.
So thanks so much.